Guide to the Bingham Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Additional Material, 1874-1984; Accession 1987-M-031
  - Family history, Series II
    This series is arranged alphabetically by family member. The materials found under each name are by or about that person. The documents contribute to an historical understanding of the Bingham family, especially Hiram Bingham III. Woodbrige Bingham's study of his father, "Hiram Bingham: A Personal History," stands out as an attempt to construct a comprehensive biography of Hiram Bingham III. An extensive interview with Woodbridge, conducted in 1972, is also included in which he discusses such topics as Hiram Bingham III's activities in Latin America and his father's relationship to his sons. Woodbridge's wife, Ursula Bingham, recounts her life in an oral history entitled "A Lady's Life: New England, Berkeley, China." "Sybil's Bones" is an interesting historical narrative which underscores the significance of the early Binghams. Some of the materials included in the series come from non-family sources. Often they are publications that have examined individual Bingham family members in historical perspective, such as "Bingham: A Loving Tribute," an account of Mrs. Hiram Bingham II's life.
    - Bingham, Alfred, "The Generation Gap" [transcription of letters between Hiram Bingham II and Hiram Bingham III, 1899-1900], 1973 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Bingham, Alfreda Mitchell, [account of Mayflower cruise], 1926 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Bingham, Hiram I [Kawaiahao Church], 1940, undated (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Bingham, Hiram II
      - "Divines -- Hiram Bingham" [biographical sketch], Undated (Box 6, Folder 4)
      - Scrapbook (Box 6, Folder 5)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Bingham, Mrs. Hiram, II, "Bingham: A Loving Tribute", [1905?] (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Bingham, Hiram III
      - Correspondence about, 1948, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      - "The Grant Family", 1931 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Illness and death, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Oahu college, 1921 (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Peru
        - Interview with Dr. Albert A. Giesecke, [1963?] (Box 6, Folder 12)
        - The National Geographic Magazine [excerpts], 1950 (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - "Sir Knight Hiram Bingham", 1983 (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Bingham, Jonathan [award nomination], 1983 (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Bingham, Lizzie [newspaper clipping of funeral], 1899 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Bingham, Ursula [oral history, Ursula Bingham, A Lady's Life: New England, Berkeley, China ], 1983 (Box 6, Folder 18)
    - Bingham, Woodbridge
      - Family historical letters [nos. 2 and 4], 1961, 1972 (Box 6, Folder 19)
      - Grove Street Cemetery, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      - "Hiram Bingham: A Personal History", 1984 (Box 7, Folder 21-26)
      - Interview about Hiram Bingham III, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 27)
      - Notebook, 1984 (Box 7, Folder 28)
      - "Personal Recollections of my Father's Interest in Latin America", 1972 (Box 7, Folder 29)
      - Research notes, 1972, undated (Box 7, Folder 30-31)
    - Brown, Lillian [letter on early Binghams], 1957 (Box 7, Folder 32)
    - Other
      - Map of Micronesia, Undated (Box 7, Folder 33)
      - Scrapbook [account of European vacation, author/compiler unkown], 1922 (Box 8, Folder 34)
      - "Sybil's Bones", Undated (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Personal, Series III
    - Diaries
      - 1887-1898 (Box 9, Folder 1-5)
      - 1910-1916 [transcription by Woodbridge Bingham, originals in main accession], 1976 (Box 9, Folder 6-10)
    - Education
      - General (Box 9, Folder 11)
      - Harvard University, 1900-1901 (Box 9, Folder 12)
      - Oahu College
        - Catalogues, 1884-1891 (Box 9, Folder 13)
        - Ranking notices, 1889-1891 (Box 9, Folder 14)
      - Phillips Academy
        - Composition, [1893 or 1894?] (Box 9, Folder 15)
        - Program, [1893 or 1894?] (Box 9, Folder 16)
        - Scholarship report, 1894 (Box 9, Folder 17)
        - Scrapbook, 1894 (Box 9, Folder 18)
      - Punahou
        - Compositions, [1891 or 1892?] (Box 9, Folder 19)
        - Drawing book, [1891 or 1892?] (Box 9, Folder 20)
        - Ranking notices, 1883-1885 (Box 9, Folder 21)
      - Yale University
        - Entrance exams, 1894-1896 (Box 9, Folder 22)
        - Lecture notes, 1897 (Box 9, Folder 23)
        - Miscellaneous (Box 9, Folder 24)
      - Height/weight charts, 1894-1896 (Box 10, Folder 25)
      - Honolulu Young Men's Christian Association, 1882, 1886 (Box 10, Folder 26)
      - Loyalty Board, 1951 (Box 10, Folder 27)
      - Notebook, 1899 (Box 10, Folder 28)
      - Notebook and regimen, [1883?] (Box 10, Folder 29)
      - Religion, Undated (Box 10, Folder 30)
      - Rocking chair, Undated (Box 10, Folder 31)
      - Scrapbooks [compiled by Hiram Bingham II or Hiram Bingham III], 1880s (Box 10, Folder 32)
      - "Views of the Hudson" [souvenir book], Undated (Box 10, Folder 33)
      - Writing book, 1879-1880 (Box 10, Folder 34)
  - Writings, Series IV
    This series is arranged by type of writing and is primarily comprised of speeches, lectures and addresses written in the early 1930s. All of the writings are by Hiram Bingham III. Most of the documents were composed during Bingham's tenure as United States senator (1924-1932) and in the years immediately following, and they broadly reflect his views on government. His anti-big government stances are evinced in these writings, especially in his criticisms of federal government's taxation policies and "paternalistic" regulations. Many of the pieces offer historical contexts for the problems of Bingham's day, as in "Why I Believe in Modification" in which Bingham offers a history of beer and wine drinking which served to criticize Prohibition laws. In this way, the writings are suggestive not only of Bingham's views on government, but also his understanding of American history. A few of the pieces relate to Bingham's interest and work in the field of aeronautics.
    - Book reviews, [1942-1943] (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Speeches, lectures, addresses - titled
      - "Aeronautics and U.S. Defense", 1933 (Box 11, Folder 2)
      - "Beware of the Donkey in the Lion's Skin", 1935 (Box 11, Folder 3)
      - "The Connecticut Idea of Government", 1935 (Box 11, Folder 4)
      - "How to Escape From More Taxes", 1932 (Box 11, Folder 5)
      - "Introducing the Chinese Minister", 1930 (Box 11, Folder 6)
      - "A Missionary Romance", 1919 (Box 11, Folder 7)
      - "Must We Have More Taxation?", 1931 (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - "Reconstruction of U.S. Government", 1932 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - "Representative Government vs. Dictatorship", 1936 (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - "Rigid Airships and Transoceanic Air Navigation", 1928 (Box 11, Folder 11)
      - "The St. Lawrence Waterway", 1932 (Box 11, Folder 12)
      - "Shall We Make Attractive Loans to the Veterans Who Are Not in Need?", 1931 (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - "Simon Bolivar, the George Washington of South America", 1930 (Box 11, Folder 14)
      - "Too Much Government", 1931 (Box 11, Folder 15)
      - "Underlying Principles of the Constitution", 1931 (Box 11, Folder 16)
      - "Why I Believe in Modification", 1931 (Box 11, Folder 17)
    - Speeches, lectures, addresses - untitled
      - Connecticut state republican convention, 1924 (Box 11, Folder 18)
      - Psi Upsilon Centenary, 1933 (Box 11, Folder 19)
      - New York dinner, 1924 (Box 11, Folder 20)
    - Testimonies [before United States Senate committees], 1934 (Box 11, Folder 21)
  - Photographs, Series V
    This series is arranged in two sections: Persons and Places. All of the photographs in the series are black and white images. Persons is organized alphabetically by individual and each folder contains photographs of the individual named, alone or with other persons. The largest number of photographs for one individual is the selection of Alfreda Mitchell Bingham, many of them from the early part of her marriage to Hiram Bingham III. Places is also organized alphabetically and includes interesting photographs of Hawaii, where Hiram Bingham III was born, as well as photographs of scenes and dorm life at Yale University in the late nineteenth century.
    - Persons
      - Billings, Luther [classmate of Hiram Bingham III], Undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
      - Bingham, Alfred [one black and white portrait], 1936 (Box 12, Folder 2)
      - Bingham, Alfreda Mitchell [includes some portraits with children], 1893-1938 (Box 12, Folder 3)
      - Bingham, Hiram II [class of Yale, 1853, several years after graduation], Undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
      - Bingham, Hiram III [with members of family], 1906-1935, undated (Box 12, Folder 5)
      - Bingham, Suzanne, 1937 (Box 12, Folder 6)
      - Bingham, Woodbridge [baby picture], Undated (Box 12, Folder 7)
      - Brewster family [parents of Mrs. Hiram Bingham II], [1865?] (Box 12, Folder 8)
      - Family [outdoors], 1927 (Box 12, Folder 9)
      - Unidentified [some from Hiram Bingham III's "Scrapbook 1899", Undated (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Places
      - Cambridge, Massachusetts, "Hill House", 1903 (Box 12, Folder 11)
      - "The Camp" [one black and white image], Undated (Box 12, Folder 12)
      - Hawaii, Undated (Box 12, Folder 13)
      - Magnolia, Massachusetts, 1945-1947 (Box 12, Folder 14)
      - Rock Creek Park [one black and white image}, 1945 (Box 12, Folder 15)
      - Woodbridge, Connecticut [one photograph of dining room), 1931 (Box 12, Folder 16)
      - Yale University, 1897 (Box 12, Folder 17)
      - Unidentified [some from Hiram Bingham III's "Scrapbook 1899"], Undated (Box 12, Folder 18)
- Additional Material, 1896-1926, 1973-1974; Accession 1994-M-074; 3.25; (2 boxes, 1 folio)
  - Hiram Bingham III
    - University of California, Berkeley: correspondence, memorabilia (loose), 1899-1900, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Scrapbook, 1898-1989 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Woodbridge Bingham
    - Correspondence from family members, 1904-1915, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - "Woodbridge Bingham, His Book": scrapbook compiled by Hiram Bingham for his son, 1901 November -1903 June (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bingham family photographs, 1896, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Mitchell-Tiffany Papers, correspondence pertaining to, 1973-1974 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - In Greece with the Classics, by William Amory Gardner, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Poster: Hiram Bingham for U.S. Senator, 1926 (Folder 3)
- Additional Material, Circa 1919; Accession 2010-M-101
  - Letters from Theodore Roosevelt to Hiram Bingham III (photocopies in scrapbook) (Box 1)
- Additional Material, 1910-1913; Accession 2013-M-027
  - Two books with manuscript notes by Hiram Bingham.
    - Up the Orinoco and Down the Magdalena by H. J. Mozans [pseud. for John Augustine Zahm]., 1910 (Box 1)
    - The Southland of North America by George Palmer Putnam, 1913 (Box 1)
- Additional Material, Circa 1860-1974; 1924-1939; Accession 2015-M-006; 1.75; 3 boxes
  - General correspondence and lists, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence and property records, Woodbridge Farms, Salem and East Haddam, Connecticut, 1922-1926, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 2-18)
  - Correspondence regarding estate of Annie O. Mitchell, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Financial records and book list of Woodbridge Bingham, 1924, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Lists, mainly of books, Circa 1938 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Services of Remembrance for Alfreda Mitchell Bingham Gregor," and cover letter, 1967, 1974 December (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Woodbridge Cemetary Association, Inc. correspondence, financial documents and copy of 1828 Constitution, 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Woodbridge Farms memorandum of equipment, maintenance, and supplies, 1913 October 1 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Photographs and prints
    - Hiram Bingham I and his brothers, 1860 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Unidentified man, tintype, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Hiram Bingham II and Minerva Clarissa Brewster Bingham in San Francisco, 1887 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Hiram Bingham II and Minerva Clarissa Brewster Bingham, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Mrs. Hiram Bingham II (Minerva Clarissa Brewster Bingham), Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Hiram Bingham III and Alfreda Mitchell Bingham, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Two unidentified men, tintype, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Hiram Bingham III and Alfreda Mitchell Bingham with their seven sons and Annie Mitchell, in Miami, 1919 April (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Hiram Bingham III and Alfreda Mitchell Bingham with five sons and Alfred and Annie Mitchell, in Jamaica, Circa 1909 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Alfred Mitchell, in uniform, Circa 1863 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Alfred Mitchell, Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Alfred Mitchell and Annie O. Tiffany Mitchell, 1887 November (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Annie O. Tiffany Mitchell, New London, Connecticut, 1887 November (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Annie O. Tiffany Mitchell, Undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - John Mumford, Jr. and Lucretia Christophers Mumford, parents of Elizabeth Mumford, wife of Nathaniel Shaw Woodbridge, Undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Louis Tiffany and family, Undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Charles Lewis Tiffany and Harriet Olivia Avery Young Tiffany, golden wedding anniversary, 1891 November 30 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Unidentified man, Undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Print of Bingham Camp, Salem, Connecticut, C. M. Sutherland, Undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Print of "Gilbertina," home of Hiram Bingham II and Minerva Clarissa Brewster Bingham in Honolulu, Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Miniatures and daguerreotypes
    - Clarissa Brewster Bingham (2 items), Undated (Box 3)
    - Hiram Bingham II, Undated (Box 3)
    - Sybil Mosely Bingham, Undated (Box 3)
    - Reverend Alfred Mitchell, 1790-1831, Undated (Box 3)
    - Alfred Mitchell, 1832-1911, Undated (Box 3)
    - Lucretia Mumford Woodbridge Mitchell, Undated (Box 3)